A Guide to the Papers of the Low Moor Iron Company
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Records
  - Inventory Store #10, 1907 June (Box Box 234)
  - H. A. Dalton, incl. Cargill correspondence, 1921 Aug. -Oct. (Box Box 235)
  - United Engineering & Foundry Co., incl. purchasing agent - castings orders; prices, 1908 July -1913 March (Box Box 235)
  - United States Geological Survey, incl. information on coal and iron production requested customary data; coke, sand, gravel, etc.; information from Secretary of Agriculture, 1911 Dec. (Box Box 235)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "U", incl. Cargill correspondence; Union Mining Co.; Union Carbide Sales Co.; Universal Portland Cement; general manager letter Senator Swanson of Virginia - against free iron and reduced pig iron rates, 1910 Sept. -1914 Aug. (Box Box 235)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "U-V", incl. Cargill correspondence; United States Rail Co.; Union Iron & Steel Co., 1910 July -1914 June (Box Box 235)
  - Virginia Pig Iron Assoc., incl. statistics, graphs, stocks, orders, blast production 1909 - 1912 (confidential), 1912 Aug. -1914 Jan. (Box Box 235)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "W", incl. Cargill - assistant treasurer and purchasing agent; George R. Wood consulting electrical Engineers; Western Electric; R. D. Wood machine parts; Wood, Vest & Co. orders, coal, wood, cement, lime; Woodward & Son - pine lumber, 1908 July -1914 Aug.; (2 folders) (Box Box 235)
  - Miscellaneous papers, incl. J. W. Montieth; report on and recommendations for prospecting around Rich Patch Mining Co. - 1924; inventory Kay Moor Mine #2, 1907 Dec. -1925 June (Box Box 236)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "W", incl. assistant treasurer; Wheeling Mold & Foundry Co.; Westinghouse Electric & Mfg. Co. - locomotive sale, fuse, 1909 Aug. -1912 Nov. (Box Box 236)
  - Western Electric and other miscellaneous "W", incl. assistant treasurer contracts, sales, problems; orders, motors, electrical equipment, cost freight damage rulings, etc.; West Virginia Mining Assoc. - "West Virginia on the brink of Labor Struggle" - pamphlet; Westinghouse West Virginia Coal Co., 1909 Oct. -1914 June; (2 folders) (Box Box 236)
  - Wood Vest & Co., incl. Cargill correspondence; purchase Kay Moor coal - sell Low Moor some coal, 1911 May -1913 Dec. (Box Box 236)
  - Braxton & McCoy - Attorneys-at-Law, incl. Means correspondence, Pulp Co. and Low Moor fight over water usages; Low Moor furnace harmed by polluted water, 1905 Feb. -1906 Sept. (Box Box 236)
  - West Virginia Pulp & Paper Co., incl. E. C. Means correspondence; Low Moor supplies with slag, lime, etc., 1910 Oct. -1914 Feb. (Box Box 236)
  - West Virginia Rail Co., West Virginia Pulp Products Co., incl. Cargill correspondence, 1910 March -1914 June (Box Box 236)
  - Westbrook Elevator Co., incl. general Manager correspondence - order for soft iron from Low Moor, 1910 May -1914 June (Box Box 236)
  - Government papers, incl. S. G. Cargill and E. C. Means correspondence; U.S. Dept. of Interior - census; U.S. Dept. of Labor - Virginia child labor laws; U.S. Dept. of Commerce - fish stocking; Interstate Commerce Commission - rate change rotation - Pennsylvania Railroad; information on mine hazards; Forest Service; Bureau of Fisheries, 1909 Jan. -1914 July; (2 folders) (Box Box 237)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "B-V", incl. Means and Cargill correspondence; Underwood Typewriter; Vehling Instruments; E. Titus - founder and machinist; Tower Buiford Electric & Mfg. Co., 1907 Sept. -1914 July (Box Box 237)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "T", incl. E. C. Means and S. G. Cargill correspondence; Transit Supply Co. select grades of pig iron; Tredegar Iron Works - Parts and supply; M. H. Treadwell - cars for slag desired; Thomas Motor Car Co. - repairs; minors release form filled out, 1907 May -1914 Aug.; (2 folders) (Box Box 237)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "F-W", incl. letters to John E. Fowle; Herman Winterer - boilers, engines, etc.; Thew Automatic Shovel specs; John E. Fowle Notebook, 1907 March -1914 June (Box Box 237)
  - Inventories, incl. warehouse inventories, June 1918 and store inventories, #12, #1, #8, Fenwick Mine, 1918 June -1925 Dec.; (9 folders) (Box Box 238)
  - Inventories, incl. Limestone #2, Dolly Ann, Hospital Limestone #1, Rented Apparatus - fire equipment, Stores 1, 2, 6, 7, 8, Fenwick, Idle Plants, Low Moor, shops, railroad equipment, scrap, stockpiles, 1920 Dec. -1923 June; (8 folders) (Box Box 239)
  - Inventories in stores #1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 9, 11, 12, 1918 June; (4 folders) (Box Box 240)
  - Purchasers, furnace slag, 1921 April -Dec. (Box Box 241)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "B-D", 1915 March -1921 Dec. (Box Box 241)
  - H. A. Dalton, 1921 Jan. -Aug. (Box Box 241)
  - Intra-company correspondence, 1909 May -1915 May (Box Box 241)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "A", 1914 Feb. -1915 May (Box Box 241)
  - Brightball, Monteith correspondence; production problems, statistics, etc., 1917 July -1920 July (Box Box 242)
  - G. T. Thayer, trustee; court cases, etc. corporation correspondence and inventory receipts, 1907 Aug. -1913 May (Box Box 242)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "B-T", incl. purchasing agent and assistant treasurer; Thew Automatic Shovel orders from Low Moor; West Virginia Pulp & Paper - furnish slag, 1908 Oct. -1920 Aug. (Box Box 242)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "C-W", incl. assistant treasurer; Walter Wallingford; notice of Low Moor owing; West Virginia Pulp & Paper - orders, 1912 Feb. -1920 Dec (Box Box 242)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "B-F", incl. assistant treasurer; Fidelity & Casuality Co. of New York - bond for liability $35,000, $350 a year; orders for pipe, rail, etc., 1920 Jan. -Nov. (Box Box 242)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "C-W", incl. assistant treasurer; iron purchases; orders for wood, 1920 June -Dec. (Box Box 242)
  - Chesapeake & Ohio Railroad - receipts and correspondence to Low Moor, 1895 -1926 (Box Box 243)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "D", incl. Dalton Nash & Co., 1899 -1902 (Box Box 243)
  - Low Moor Iron Co. correspondence to E. C. Means, 1889 -1906 (Box Box 243)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "C, H, P", incl. Hickman Williams Co.; Courtland Babcock Co. - note brokers; Clark Steel Co.; Corrigan, McKinney Co., 1894 -1914 (Box Box 243)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence "C", incl. Cleveland Cliffs Iron Co.; Clifton Forge Grocery Co.; Crescent Supply Co.; Covington Machine Co., Cincinnati, Hamilton & Dayton Railway; Cincinnati Iron Store Co.; Chapman Iron Coal & Coke Co.; Capital City Supply Co.; Cement Machinery Co.; Cash & Allen Flower; A. M. Castle & Co Iron & Steel, 1895 -1906; (3 folders) (Box Box 243)
  - Low Moor Iron Co. correspondence from Kay Moor Mines, 1906 (Box Box 243)
  - George W. Risen: Correspondence and Business Card re His Black Real Estate Agency and Employment Bureau, 1902 (Box Box 244)
  - Correspondence, 1899 -1919; (2 folders) (Box Box 244)
  - Book Ledger and Monthly Time Books, 1885 -1888, 1917 (Box Box 244)
  - Miscellaneous, 1901 -1925 (Box Box 244)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1886 -1895; (6 folders) (Box Box 245)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1893 -1931, n.d.; (6 folders) (Box Box 246)
  - Blank Deeds, Contracts, Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box Box 246)
  - Low Moor Iron Company: Blueprints
    - "Atlas Tie Plate", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Boiler For Low Moor....From Newport News", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Brake for Switching Locomotive", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Cameron Regular Piston Pump", 1906 (Box Oversize)
    - "Car Changing Scale" (2 copies), n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, Backbone, Virginia - Pipe Line," w/attached letter, 1910-1911 (Box Oversize)
    - "Crank High Speed Engine-X2022A", 1907 Aug 28 (Box Oversize)
    - "Coal Handling Machinery", 1897 Jul 19 (Box Oversize)
    - "12 x 22 x 13 x 20 Compound Piston Pump", 1907 Dec 19 (Box Oversize)
    - "Compressed Air Motor" and "Compressed Air Locomotive" (Box Oversize)
    - "Cross Section of Cable Conveyor....", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Crossing for Steam & Electric Railways" (2 copies), 1899 Sep (Box Oversize)
    - "42" Cylinder, 42" x 87' x 60" Vertical Blowing Engine" (Box Oversize)
    - "Detail of 8" Pitch Steel Chain with Cross Bar and 24" x 8" Scraper", 1902 Jun 23 (Box Oversize)
    - "12" x 8" x 10" Duplex Pumping Engine", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Elevations of Elevator for Handling Iron Ore", 1895 Mar 13 (Box Oversize)
    - "Fire Clay Brick Flaked & Fine Ground, All Shapes" (Box Oversize)
    - "18' Fire Brick Stove Foote-Lammond Type" (Box Oversize)
    - "Foundation for 325 HP Vertical Water Tube Boiler", 1899 Sep 8 (Box Oversize)
    - "The Frost Pneumatic Pump", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Furnace 'C', Low Moor Co.", 1905 Jan (Box Oversize)
    - "'G' Type Compressor," w/attached letter, 1912, 1925 (Box Oversize)
    - "General Arrangement of Four Boilers", 1900 May 5 (Box Oversize)
    - "General Arrangement for 205-K.C. with Lifting Magnet (Crane)", 1921 Mar 8 (Box Oversize)
    - "Hand Car with Roller Bearings", 1891 May 21 (Box Oversize)
    - "Howe Standard Railroad Track Scale," w/attached letter, Howe Scale Company to Low Moor Iron Co., 1917 Jun 26 (Box Oversize)
    - "16" Manganese Steel Mine Car Wheel" (3 sheets), 1902 May 15 (Box Oversize)
    - "Motors Built for 30-60 HP Service by Crocker-Wheeler Co.," w/attached circular, 1902, 1903 (Box Oversize)
    - "No. 6 Crusher...," w/attached letter from Allis Chalmers Co. to Low Moor Iron Company, 1899, 1903 (Box Oversize)
    - "By the Otis Elevator Company", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Ore Washing Machinery", 1894 Dec 19 (Box Oversize)
    - "Pat. C. B. 45 to be Used When 10 x 5 x 10 Pump Is Wanted", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Pierpont Serial Water Tube Boiler", 1895 Jun 24 (Box Oversize)
    - "Piston Rods for 42" x 87" x 60" Vertical Blowing Engine", 1901 Jan 7 (Box Oversize)
    - "Profile of Incline for the Low Moor Iron Co. of Virginia, Kay Moor #1, New Opening", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Rail Benders for Mines...." (Box Oversize)
    - "Railroad Track Scale (3 views)," w/2 attached notes, 1887 (Box Oversize)
    - "Railroad Track Scale (2 views)", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "Railroad Track Scale (4 views)", n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "14 x 10 x 18 Regular Pattern Piston Pump", 1908 Mar 16 (Box Oversize)
    - "60" x 40" x 28" Revolving Ore Dryer", 1899 Jul 8 (Box Oversize)
    - "M. & T. Scale," Drawing 79 and Drawing 80," w/attached items (Box Oversize)
    - "Scheme for Pig Iron Conveyor and Breaker", 1906 May 2 (Box Oversize)
    - "Single Side Crank High Speed Engine-X2007A", 1907 Dec (Box Oversize)
    - "Single Valve Side Crank High Speed Engine-X2009A", 1908 Jan (Box Oversize)
    - "Single Valve Side Crank High Speed Engine-X2012A", 1907 Aug (Box Oversize)
    - "Single Valve Side Crank High Speed Engine-X2020A", 1908 Jan (Box Oversize)
    - "Six Ton Monitor", 1918 Apr (Box Oversize)
    - "Slide Valve-X2014A", 1907 Jul 1 (Box Oversize)
    - "Solid Crossing, Design #6", 1901 Aug (Box Oversize)
    - "Special Boot for Handling Iron Ore", 1895 Mar 1 (Box Oversize)
    - "2300 Steel Brushed Roller Chain Belt with #10 Steel Apron", 1910 Nov (Box Oversize)
    - "Suspension Railroad Track Scale (4 views)," w/attached circulars, n.d. (Box Oversize)
    - "9 degree Tie-rail Frog", 1918 Jun 23 (Box Oversize)
    - "12 Ton Shovel," w/two attached letters, 1904-1906 (Box Oversize)
    - "Worthington 6"c. Volute Pump", 1902 (Box Oversize)
  - Low Moor Iron Company: General
    - Map: Chesapeake and Ohio Railway (Box Oversize)
    - Record of Blasts, 1908-1909 (Box Oversize)